Guide to the Diane Weddington Papers, 1956-2014 RL.01356
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Diane Weddington papers
1956-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weddington, Diane
RL.01356
91.5 Linear Feet
Diane Weddington worked as a journalist and religion editor at the Contra Costa Times in the 1980s-1990s. She has also taught courses in journalism, public policy, new media, and ethics. Collection includes Weddington's published articles, research clippings, reporter notes, and other publications and materials from her journalism career, divinity school studies, background material for arts journalism, and materials documenting Weddington's educational and teaching careers. Topics represented include the gay and lesbian community in San Francisco, the ordination of women and gay clergy, the women's rights movement, domestic violence and child abuse, Alzheimer's Disease, and other miscellaneous subjects.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Diane Weddington Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2014.
Biographical Note
Diane Weddington attended Duke University and Duke Divinity School and worked as a reporter and a religion editor at the Contra Costa Times. She has also taught courses at Duke University and other institutions on media and public policy, public policy writing, journalism principles, new media and media law and ethics, as well as published a book on Alzheimer's Disease.
Collection Overview
The collection includes a variety of materials, ranging from Weddington's published articles to clippings of other articles used in her research. The coverage of the homosexual community in and around San Francisco is represented in two series; the first being Coverage of Gay Clergy in the Church. This series includes legal proceedings by the Lutheran Church against gay clergy, as well as Weddington's own reporter notebooks from her time covering the subject. A second series, Coverage of Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual Communities, includes materials from Weddington's involvement in the National Lesbian and Gay Journalist Association and the Frameline film festival. Also included in this series are coverage of the blackballing of gay and lesbian news by the Contra Costa Times, business directories from San Francisco, local gay pride events, and mainstream coverage of gays and lesbians in America.
The series on Weddington's Research, Clippings, and Reporting from Various Projects includes materials from her religion beat at the Contra Costa Times, as well as other internal correspondence and clippings from her work at the newspaper. Subjects include general women's news, as well as articles on domestic violence and rape, child abuse, Satanism, recovered memory phenomena, and women's rights. Also included in this series are materials from Weddington's many projects, including the War Tax Resistance campaign, Diablo Valley study groups and clubs, Journalists Exchange on Aging, and gardening. Finally, this series includes materials from Weddington's coverage of the visit of Pope John Paul II to San Francisco in 1987.
Women in the Church includes materials from Weddington's own involvement in the women's ordination movement in the Episcopal Church, as well as her clippings of coverage regarding women and religion during the 1970s-1980s. Also related and included in this series are Weddington's materials from her time as a student at the Divinity School at Duke University in the 1970s.
Weddington's Published Articles and Reporter's Notes appear to date largely from 1986-1992, although many articles and most of her notes are undated. These clippings from the Contra Costa Times along with news wires reveal the breadth of Weddington's journalism, with topics ranging from the religion section to breaking news about traffic accidents. The materials are not sorted or arranged in any way. Along with clippings and reporter's notebook pages, the series also includes some correspondence from readers, internal Contra Costa Times photography requests, press releases, and other miscellaneous pages used by Weddington in her work.
Finally, the Correspondence series includes both electronic (print-outs) and postal correspondence. One part of the series consists of dot matrix printer printouts of internal communications between the staff and management of the Contra Costa Times. Weddington writes that this material documents the bias against gays and lesbians, as well as the regular workflow of the newspaper in terms of scheduling reporters, meeting deadlines, internal gossip, and so on. Another portion of the series contains letters, greeting cards, and other personal and professional correspondence. These have been arranged by year but not sorted further.
Accession (2014-0169) contains materials documenting Weddington's education and teaching careers, personal and professional correspondence, as well as materials relating to her work as a reporter, material related to her book on Alzheimer's disease, and work on the arts for the National Parks Service.
Included are materials from her grade school studies, undergraduate career at Duke University, work at Duke Divinity School, journalism coursework at the University of Missouri, and graduate studies at Berkeley in journalism and law. Teaching materials include courses taught at Contra Costa Community college on journalism and ethics. She has also taught couses on media and public policy. Also included are clippings and extensive research materials from her arts journalism in California, including work done for the Contra Costa Times.
San Francisco (Calif.); Women's rights -- United States; Child abuse -- Prevention; Recovered memory; Ordination of women -- Episcopal Church; Clippings (information artifacts); Newspaper publishing; Reporters and reporting; Women and journalism; Women and religion; Sexism in religion; Homosexuality -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Ordination of gays -- Evangelical Lutheran Church in America; John Paul II, Pope, 1920-2005 -- Travel; Contra Costa Times; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Weddington, Diane; Duke University. History; Duke University. Divinity School
- Coverage of gay clergy in the church, 1970s-1990s, 2 boxes
  - Lutheran Church proceedings against gay clergy, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Binders (refoldered) with legal proceedings (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Related materials and publications (Box 1)
    - Reporters notebooks from Weddington's coverage (Box 1)
  - Homosexuality and the Church (publications, clippings, etc.), 1970s-1990s (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Religion talks and programs, 1995 (Box 2)
- Coverage of gay, lesbian, and bisexual communities in the San Francisco area, 1980s-2000s, 2 boxes
  - National Lesbian and Gay Journalist Association founding and early conventions, 1992-1996 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Clippings regarding gay, lesbian, and bisexual news and events, 1980s-2000s (5 folders) (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes coverage of the Contra Costa Times blackballing of gay and lesbian news.
  - Mainstream magazine coverage of gays, lesbians, and bisexuals, 1989-2000 (Box 3)
  - Frameline (San Francisco International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival) press folders, 2004-2006 (Box 3)
  - International Lesbian and Gay Freedom Day materials, 1981-1990 (Box 3)
  - San Francisco business directories for the gay and lesbian community, 1984 and 1994 (Box 3)
- Research, clippings, and reporting from various projects, 1980-2000s, 7 boxes
  - Coverage and materials from Pope John Paul II's visit to San Francisco Bay area, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Contests (entry forms, San Francisco journalists), 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Contra Costa Times email printouts, reporter scheduling, etc., 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Letters answered, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Journalists Exchange on Aging, 1993-2004 (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Children's Garden project, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Diablo Valley Hassadah Study Group, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Gardening, 1989-1999 (Box 4)
  - Masculinity, undated (Box 5)
  - Sequoia newsletters, 1995-2004 (Box 5)
  - War Tax Resistance materials, including campaign organizing and newsletters, 1980-1987 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Panels, speeches, other activities, 1982-2000 (Box 5)
  - Buttons and badges from various events and causes (Box 5)
  - Women's rights programs and conferences, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Publications and articles about women's liberation, 1970s-1990s (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Bizarre mail received while a religion editor, 1986-1992 (Box 6)
  - Erhard Seminars Training Manual, 1977 (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Religion Newswriters Association newsletters, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
  - Clippings and publications regarding Satanism (Box 7)
  - Clippings and publications regarding recovered memories (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Clippings and publications regarding child abuse or violence against women (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Clippings and publications regarding child abuse or violence against women (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Spiritual aspects of ritual abuse cassette tape, undated (Box 8)
  - Clippings and publications regarding women,general (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Clippings and publications regarding women, general (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Articles about women and religion (Box 9)
  - Religion and Public Affairs directory, 1987 (Box 9)
- Women in the church, 1970s-1980s, 2 boxes
  - Women at Duke Divinity School
    - First Interseminary, Yale, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Second Interseminary, Duke, 1974 (Box 10)
    - First Grailville (Box 10)
    - Sojourners/Duke (Box 10)
    - Nonsexist liturgies (Box 10)
    - General communications from Duke Divinity, including Sojourners (Box 10)
    - Response newsletters, 1973-1976 (Box 10)
    - Worship materials, etc., 1970s-1980s (Box 10)
    - Senior Sermon, Duke Divinity School, 1976 (Box 62)
  - Episcopal women's ordination
    - General convention, Louisville, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Virginia Theological Seminary caucus, 1973 (Box 10)
    - St. John Witness, New York City, 1973 December (Box 10)
    - New York City National Coordinating Committee, 1974 February (Box 10)
    - Riverside Communion, 1974 October (Box 10)
    - General convention, Minneapolis, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Deliberation newsletter, 1974-1976 (Box 10)
    - Wendt/Cheek article, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Mentor, 1976 April (Box 10)
    - Women's ordination, general articles (Box 10)
    - Post-1976 materials (Box 10)
    - Caucus newsletter, 1974-1976 (Box 11)
    - Katrina Swanson-post Philadelphia actions (Box 11)
    - Official Studies, 1966-1978 (Box 11)
    - Midwestern caucus, 1974 (Box 11)
    - House of Bishops, 1974 August (Box 11)
    - Philadelphia convention, 1974 (Box 11)
    - Ohio caucus, 1974 October (Box 11)
    - Virginia Theological Seminary caucus, 1973 March (Box 11)
    - Witness, 1974-1979 (Box 11)
    - Publications and programs (Box 11)
    - Cup Bearing License, 1978-1979 (Box 62)
    - Postulancy, 1977-1980 (Box 62)
  - Women in Religion materials
    - Publications and notes, 1970s (Box 11)
    - Women's groups (South Hayward Parrish), 1977-1978 (Box 11)
    - Women and mental health, UC Davis, 1979 February (Box 11)
    - Assertiveness training, undated (Box 11)
    - Women and language, 1972-1982 (Box 11)
    - Harassment, 1977-1982 (Box 11)
    - Women in Media conference, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Changing psychology of men and women, 1979 May (Box 11)
- Published articles and reporter's notes, 1986-1992 and undated, 7 boxes
  Materials include clippings of Weddington's published pieces, largely from the Contra Costa Times, dating from 1986-1992 (and undated). These clippings, while in excellent condition, are unsorted and in many cases undated. Topics include religion and religious coverage, cultural events and exhibits, breaking news, community calendars, and numerous other areas.
  Along with the actual clippings, Weddington frequently included her notes from particular articles, as well as miscellaneous materials such as press releases, photograph requests, correspondence, and other items. These supplemental materials are also unsorted and undated.
  - Published articles and reporter's notes (Box 12-17)
- Correspondence, 1985-1998 and undated, 1 box
  - Internal Contra Costa Times email correspondence, 1986-1992 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1985-1998 and undated (Box 19)
- Accession (2014-0169)
  - Published Articles, Book Chapter, Book, Training Exercise, Speeches, 1980-2005 (Box 20)
  - Emails, Correspondence, List of '60s Duke Divinity School graduates, 2002-2008 (Box 21)
  - Bay Area Film Festival Programs and Notes, 1989-2014 (Box 22)
  - Duke Course Readings: Race, Media, and Public Policy, 2006-2013 (Box 23)
  - Faculty Notes and Student Advisory Materials: Contra Costa Community College, 1999-2001 (Box 24)
  - Class Notes, 1969-1976 (Box 25)
  - Sermons and Articles by Weddington; Class Notes, 1976-1980 (Box 26)
  - Episcopal Ordination Courses, 1978-1979 (Box 26)
  - Journalism Coursework Class Notes, 1974-1976 (Box 27)
  - Missourian Articles, 1974-1976 (Box 27)
  - Arts Journalism and Research, California, 1995-2009 (Box 28)
  - Personal Correspondence, 2004-2013 (Box 29)
  - World Vision Board Member Materials, 2004-2013 (Box 29)
  - Teaching Materials, 1978-2013 (Box 30)
  - Arts Journalism, 1978-2013 (Box 30)
  - Divinity School Notebooks, 1970s (Box 31)
  - Applied Ethics, 1990-2012 (Box 32)
  - Contra Costa Times Materials, 1986-1992 (Box 33)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1993-2003 (Box 34)
  - Brill's Content Magazine (Box 35)
  - Journalism Materials (Box 35)
  - Notebooks: First-Twefth Grade, 1956-1968 (Box 36)
  - Film Journalism Including Spike Lee Interview, 1995-2009 (Box 37)
  - PhD Studies at Graduate Theological Union (Box 38)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 39)
  - Professional Organizations, 1976-1986 (Box 40)
  - Carlyle Marney Notebooks and Course Work, 1973-1981 (Box 41)
  - Duke Undergraduate Course Work, 1968-1972 (Box 42, Box 45)
  - Art Exhibits Reviewed (Box 43)
  - St. Mary's College Materials and Arts Grant, 1978-2000 (Box 44)
  - High School Classwork, 1967-1970 (Box 46, Box 52, Box 53)
  - Alzheimer's Book Research, 1990s (Box 47)
  - Spirituality and Health (Box 48)
  - Background Material for Arts Reporting (Box 49, Box 55)
  - Correspondence, Bioethics, and Reporting Research (Box 50)
  - Publisher Correspondence, Conferences, Writing, Manuscripts, 1970-2012 (Box 51, Box 62)
  - Personal Correspondence, 2002-2004 (Box 54)
  - Reading Materials for Duke Courses Taught (Box 56)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 57-61)